Minoru Yamasaki Papers
Minoru Yamasaki Papers
1961-1965
Yamasaki, Minoru, 1912-1986.
0.5 linear feet
Papers of the artist, architect. Includes project files with photographs and working papers, undated manuscripts, and other material. Projects include Dhahran Air Terminal in Saudi Arabia, the United States Pavilion at the World's Fair in Seattle, Washington, and the World Trade Center in New York City.
148772
Biographical History
Minoru Yamasaki (1912-1986) was an American architect. Born in Seattle, Washington, he studied at the University of Washington (graduated 1929) and at New York University. He began his career working for Gitchen and Kelly (1935-1937) and teaching watercolor at New York University. In 1937 he moved to Shreve, Lamb and Harmon, designers of the Empire State Building, and then in 1945 he moved to Detroit to work for the firm of Smith, Hinchman, and Gryll. Four years later he became a partner in Limweber, Yamasaki, and Hellmuth and soon after opened his own firm, Yamasaki & Associates, based in Birmingham, Michigan.
Yamasaki's work, which is distinctly modern in tone, includes banks, schools, auditoriums, airport terminals, libraries, conference centers, and consulates. He was the designer of the United States Science Pavilion for the Seattle World's Fair and of the New York World Trade Center Towers 1 and 2, which were destroyed in the September 11, 2001 attacks. Yamasaki was one of the most prominent architects of the 20th century and his firm, Yamasaki & Associates, continues to do business today.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Minoru Yamasaki Papers includes correspondence, subject files, projects, and manuscripts. Correspondence consists of a single outgoing letter. Subject files contains a radio broadcast made by Yamasaki for the Voice of America. Projects contains photographs and data for a number of Yamasaki's works, including the Dhahran Air Terminal in Saudi Arabia, the United States Pavilion at the World's Fair in Seattle, Washington, and the World Trade Center in New York City. Manuscripts contains two manuscripts by Yamasaki.
Arrangement of the Collection
Each series is arranged alphabetically by title or topic.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of architects. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Yamasaki, Minoru, 1912-1986.; Yamasaki & Associates.; Architecture, modern.; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century.; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.); Manuscripts for publication.; Photoprints.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing, 1965 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Voice of America radio broadcast, undated (Box 1)
- Projects
  - Dhahran Civil Air Terminal, Dhahran, Saudi Arabia, 1963 (Box 1)
  - McGregor Memorial Community Conference Center, Wayne State University, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Consolidated Gas Company office building, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Northwestern National Life Insurance Company office building, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Reynolds Metal Company Regional Sales Office, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Temple Building, North Shore Congregational Israel, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Terminal Building, Lambert-St. Louis Airport, 1962 (Box 1)
  - United States Science Pavilion, Seattle, Washington, 1964 (Box 1)
  - World Trade Center, Port Authority of New York, 1964 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - "The Challenge to the Arts", undated (Box 1)
  - "Report on Wascana Centre", undated (Box 1)